<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Discourse of the dukedom of Modena containing the origine, antiquity, government, manners and qualities of the people : as also the temperature of the climate, with the nature and fertility of the soil.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1674</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 52 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A36100</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D1603</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R890</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12264923</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12264923</idno>
            <idno type="VID">57987</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A36100)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 57987)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 181:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Discourse of the dukedom of Modena containing the origine, antiquity, government, manners and qualities of the people : as also the temperature of the climate, with the nature and fertility of the soil.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 30 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.C. for William Crook ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1674.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Modena (Italy) --  Description and travel.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:57987:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:57987:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Diſcourſe Of the DUKEDOM of MODENA. CONTAINING The
<list>
                  <item>Origine,</item>
                  <item>Antiquity,</item>
                  <item>Government,</item>
                  <item>Manners, and</item>
                  <item>Qualities</item>
               </list> Of the People. As alſo, The Temperature of the CLIMATE, WITH The Nature and Fertility of the SOIL.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>J. C.</hi> for <hi>William Crook,</hi> at the Green Dragon without Temple-bar. 1674.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb facs="tcp:57987:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:57987:2"/>
            <head>A DISCOURSE Of the Dukedom of Modena.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>NTIquITY was ſo ignorant, as to divide the whole World into two parts onely, <hi>viz. ASIA</hi> and <hi>E<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ROPE;</hi> comprehending <hi>Africa</hi> under <hi>ASIA,</hi> as <hi>Eratosthenes</hi> an Author of as great eſteem as anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity; ſome under <hi>E<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ROPE,</hi> as <hi>Iſocrates</hi> in his Panegyrique, and others mentioned in <hi>Salust, Lucan,</hi> and S. <hi>Austin de civitate Dei:</hi> but the moſt celebrated Diviſion was into three parts; <hi>E<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ROPE, ASIA,</hi> and <hi>AFRICA</hi> or <hi>Libya;</hi> and this
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:57987:3"/>was approv'd both by ancient and modern Authors. So that it appears, Coſmography was unacquainted with any other Diviſion of the Univerſe, till that the knowing <hi>Genoueſe,</hi> about two Centuries ago, did furniſh it with a Fourth, by his diſcovery of <hi>AMERICA,</hi> the moſt uſual, but improper name: for <hi>Columbus,</hi> after his ineffectual addreſſes to the States of <hi>Genoua, Anno</hi> 1486, and to <hi>Henry the</hi> 7<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> and their abſolute refuſal; he ſpun out ſix years in patient attendance at the Court of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stile,</hi> where at laſt he was furniſhed out with three Veſſels more proper for Diſcovery than Conqueſt. And thus he firſt found it out, and led the way to the reſt. But <hi>Americus Veſputius</hi> the <hi>Florentine,</hi> a man old in years, but young in courage, employed therein by <hi>Emanuel</hi> King of <hi>Portugal,</hi> ſurveyed a great part of the Continent by the light he had from <hi>Columbus</hi> the firſt Diſcoverer; yet the <hi>Floren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine</hi> prov'd the Godfather, and call'd it <hi>AMERICA,</hi> to perpetuate his own Name, and eternize his Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory. <hi>John Cabot</hi> a <hi>Venetian,</hi> in behalf of <hi>Henry</hi> the 7<hi rend="sup">th</hi>, diſcovered all the North-eaſt coaſt thereof, and touched many places <hi>Americus</hi> ne'r ſaw. And although theſe three <hi>Italians</hi> were by three ſeveral Monarchs employed to finde out this Fourth part of the World, it is ſo vaſt a Continent, that the Southern part is to this day altogether unknown; and uſually in our Planiſpheres and Maps call'd <hi>Terra Australis incognita.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>E<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ROPE</hi> as to its Magnitude, (in the opinion of Coſmographers, who run all in the ſame current
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:57987:3"/>or ſtream) is inferiour to the other three; though to none of them, if you conſider the moderate and wholeſome Temperature of the Air, together with the prodigious fertility of its Soyl; the two once-famous <hi>Romane</hi> and <hi>Greek</hi> Monarchies; the Study and Improvement of Arts both Liberal and Mecha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nical; the Affluence of all things that conduce ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to the Support or Pleaſure of Man; or above all, the Purity and Sincerity of the Chriſtian Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion univerſally profeſs'd in all the Dominions thereof; beſides the well-regulated Government of their Realms, their Kings being Abſolute Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchs, but not Arbitrary Tyrants; and the men happie Subjects, not miſerable Slaves; which keeps us from that Tyranny, Slavery, Injuſtice, frequent Bribery, Beggery and Barbariſm, which like an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>undation hath overflown all the <hi>Aſiatick, African,</hi> and <hi>American</hi> parts, when they groan'd under the Yoke of their Idolatrous and Sanguinary Princes and Governours. <hi>Par nihil Europe, nihil eſt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>ITALY is is a Region, that, among many other advantageous Elogies, is on all hands held to be the <hi>Eden</hi> of <hi>Europe,</hi> the Garden or Paradiſe of this North-weſt part of the World. This <hi>Peninſula</hi> or Demi-Iſland, formerly the abſolute and redoubted Empreſs of the major part of the then-known habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table World, yet may compare, as now it is, nay exceed the moſt of the other Kingdoms of <hi>Aſia, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frica,</hi> or <hi>America.</hi> 'Tis ſituate in a moſt Tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Clime; and for the amoenity of its Cities, the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:57987:4"/>commodiouſneſs for Commerce and Negotiations, the deliciouſneſs of its Fountains and Aqueducts, the fertility of its well-cultivated Fields, inſomuch that in ſome places they have three Harveſts in one year; the Uniformity and Statelineſs of Fabriques, and the rare Architecture and rich Furniture and Ornaments of its Temples, and many other Delica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies to gratifie the <hi>gusto</hi> as to Fruits and rare Wines, with other Varieties too numerous to be crowded into the narrow confines of our intended Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe.</p>
            <p>And in this Paradiſe or Garden of <hi>Europe</hi> there is a ſmall <hi>Terroir,</hi> or pleaſant ſpot of ground, known by the name of <hi>MODENA;</hi> where we will take the <hi>freſco</hi> for ſome time, and give you our Senti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments upon a ſtrict Survey of what ſhall occur as obſervable during this our <hi>Promenade;</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon make ſome Remarques, which will prove the moſt uſeful Materials, and moſt conducive to the compliment of this our preſent Eſſay.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>MODENA</hi> is the Modern appellation; but it is better known to the Ancients by the name of <hi>Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tina;</hi> as <hi>Livie, Cicero, Pliny,</hi> &amp;c. Some read it <hi>Motina;</hi> as <hi>Antoninus</hi> and <hi>Dio: Strabo</hi> and <hi>Ptole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> commonly <hi>Modena, à movendo</hi> (ſaith <hi>Merula</hi> in his Coſmography) <hi>ut quidam inſulſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jiciunt, eo quòd Diluvio quondam tota fuerit ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merſa, qua de re dignus Autore ſuo Verſiculus.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>Mutina ſubmerſa fuit olim gurgitis unda.</q>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:57987:4"/>
            <p>Call'd <hi>Modena</hi> (a fooliſh conceit) becauſe it was once drowned with a Deluge. The more probable Conjecture is, that it was nam'd <hi>à movendo,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is at this day ſomewhat removed from the ſituation of the ancient Citie, which the <hi>Longobards</hi> did totally ruinate and demoliſh.</p>
            <p>The City of <hi>Mutina,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Dukedom of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dena</hi> at preſent contains the Citie of <hi>Modena</hi> and <hi>Reggio,</hi> with the Lands and Territories thereunto adjoyning. They are both pleaſantly ſituated in that part of <hi>Lombardy</hi> called <hi>Ciſpadana,</hi> or as in their own Dialect vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garly. <hi>Diqua del Po,</hi> on this ſide of the river <hi>Po.</hi>
               </note> now <hi>MODENA,</hi> was firſt erected by the <hi>Etrurians</hi> or <hi>Tuſci,</hi> now cal'd <hi>Toſcans</hi> a people of <hi>Italy;</hi> and they waging War with the <hi>Galli Boii,</hi> were expelled thence by them, who after that poſſeſſed it; and they being profligate by the Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorious Arm of the <hi>Romane</hi> Conquerors, it was by them made a Colony, together with <hi>Parma,</hi> in the 570 or 571 year after the Building of <hi>Rome,</hi> as <hi>Livie</hi> and other Hiſtorians affirm, (<hi>Quintus Fabius Labio</hi> and <hi>Marcus Claudius</hi> being at that time Conſuls) who in ſeveral places make very honourable men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of it; an infallible teſtimony that it was both rich and potent: which truth is more at large con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm'd by the various Inſcriptions and ancient Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles that are yet everywhere extant, and expos'd to the view of all Travellers.</p>
            <p>This Citie was ſufficiently illuſtrated and made famous in thoſe times, for the firſt Battel between <hi>Antonie</hi> and <hi>C. Octavianus Caeſar,</hi> who was then but
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:57987:5"/>a Stripling or <hi>Tyro</hi> in War, and not above Eighteen years, and yet made Head of a new League againſt <hi>Antonius,</hi> whom the Senate lookt upon with an ill eye, as a common and dangerous Enemy. This happened in the year 711, when <hi>Antonius</hi> beſieg'd <hi>C. Brutus</hi> in this Citie; but by the aſſiſtance of <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar Octavianus</hi> he gain'd the Victory. The mana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging of the whole War was left to <hi>Hirtius</hi> and <hi>Pan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa,</hi> at that time Conſuls. The fortune of the day was ſo well managed on both ſides, that <hi>Antonie</hi> loſt the Field, and the Conſuls their Lives; <hi>Caeſar Octavianus</hi> remaining abſolute Commander of a puiſſant and numerous Army, into whoſe favour he by his dexterity ſo cunningly inſinuated him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and made ſo good improvement of his Talent, and ſuch advantage of the opportunity, that this prov'd the Baſis and Foundation of his future Grandeur. But afterwards, when the ſaid <hi>C. Octa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vianus, M. Antonius,</hi> and <hi>M. Aemilius Lepidus</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into the Society of the <hi>Triumvirate,</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon the Citie had very courſe uſage, and was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd to very great Slaughter, by <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Great, becauſe that it favoured <hi>Maxentius:</hi> but the Victory being once obtain'd, it was reſtor'd, and the Chriſtians became poſſeſſed of it; it was dignified with an Epiſcopal Seat, and <hi>Geminianus</hi> a Learned man made Biſhop thereof. After this, it was reduced to aſhes by the Inundation of the <hi>Goths</hi> and <hi>Lombards,</hi> a furious and barbarous people, as S. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> relates the Story, affirming that he ſaw <hi>Modena</hi> with the reſt of the adjacent places upon
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:57987:5"/>the <hi>Via Aemilia,</hi> ſuffer a total devaſtation. But theſe Barbarians were afterwards expulſed by the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour <hi>Charles</hi> the Great, who eſtabliſhed his ſon <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pin</hi> King of <hi>Italy;</hi> and then the Citizens of <hi>Modena,</hi> whoſe names were engraven on the gates, quitting their ſad but ſecure Retirements, whither they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fin'd themſelves during the diſtractions and tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moils that <hi>Italy</hi> then labour'd under, took counſel how to rebuild this Citie: and in proceſs of time they erected it in that form as now it appears in. They being now their own Maſters, free from the Vaſſalage of an inſulting Enemy, and ſolely at their own diſpoſal, and having the Juriſdiction within themſelves, they onely retain'd the <hi>Romane</hi> name; but yet were not ſo much at reſt, but they had ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Skirmiſhes with their Neighbours, eſpecially the people of <hi>Bologna,</hi> about the Limits and Bounds of their Country.</p>
            <p>During the Diſtractions and Troubles of <hi>Italy</hi> between the Emperour and the Popes, <hi>Guido</hi> the Popes Legate, and then Biſhop thereof, conſign'd it over to <hi>Azo</hi> one of the Houſe of <hi>Este,</hi> Lord of <hi>Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rara, Anno</hi> 1304, the Pope conſenting to it, upon the annual payment of the Tribute of 10000 Crowns. Since which time it hath been for the moſt part in the power of that Houſe; <hi>Berſius</hi> Marqueſs of <hi>Ferrara</hi> being created Duke of <hi>Mutina</hi> by the Emperour <hi>Frederick</hi> the third. <hi>Anno</hi> 1312, ſhe had the Family of the <hi>Mirandulae</hi> her Maſters, by the Authority of the Emperour, <hi>anno</hi> 1319. the <hi>Bonacelſii</hi> Tyrants of <hi>Mantua</hi> being compelled
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:57987:6"/>thereunto by the help and aſſiſtance of the <hi>Guelphi. Anno</hi> 1331, the <hi>Pii</hi> governed her, at firſt under the name of Captains, afterwards of Princes. Further<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more, <hi>anno</hi> 1336, the <hi>Ateſtini</hi> or Family <hi>d'Esteé</hi> ſucceeded them, who were Marqueſſes of <hi>Ferrara,</hi> by the Popes leave and permiſſion; and they go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verned it till the year 1510, when Pope <hi>Julius</hi> 11 took the Citie, and gave it to <hi>Maximilian</hi> 1, Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour, by whom it was afterwards, <hi>anno</hi> 1514, hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pothequ'd to Pope <hi>Leo</hi> the tenth, for 10000 Crowns. Laſtly, in the year 1527, when <hi>Clement</hi> the Pope was beſieg'd by the lmperialiſts, it was retaken by the Victorious Arms of the <hi>Atestini,</hi> or Family of <hi>Esté,</hi> by whom it was increaſed with Buildings, Walls, and fenced with Ditches; and grew up by degrees to the preſent ſplendour, ſtate and gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deur.</p>
            <p>Thus far the ancient Authors, particularly <hi>Livy;</hi> and the modern alſo, as <hi>Blondus Corius, Platina, Sabellicus, Volaterranus,</hi> and <hi>Leandro;</hi> beſides what we finde in the Annals of the Citie, and <hi>Bologna</hi> likewiſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>MODENA</hi> is marſhalled by <hi>Pliny</hi> in the eighth Region of <hi>Italy,</hi> and call'd by <hi>Ptolemy</hi> a Citie of <hi>Gallia Togata;</hi> being waſhed by the Rivulet or Brook <hi>Formigo.</hi> It was heretofore ſituated ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what higher towards the Mountains than now it is at preſent, as appears by the ruines of ſome antiqua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted edifices ſtanding ſomewhat diſtant from the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient <hi>Modena,</hi> as <hi>Leandro</hi> intimates more at large.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:57987:6"/>
            <p>The Citie is noble and ſplendid, of an orbicular form, ſeated in a Plain not far from the <hi>Apennines,</hi> which are called the Back, or rather Back-bone of <hi>Italy,</hi> becauſe, like the <hi>Spina</hi> in the body, they divide <hi>Italy</hi> into two parts or ſides, Weſt or North. It is beautified with a Cathedral Church, the doors whereof are worthy admiration for many things, but particularly for the famous Marble-ſtatues of <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve.</hi> It flouriſheth with the dignity of an Epiſcopacie, which is ſubject to the Archbiſhop of <hi>Bologna;</hi> and is alſo adorn'd with an Academy, in which <hi>Azo</hi> the Civilian taught the Imperial Law. It is a pleaſant Soyl, abounding with Fruits and Grains of all ſorts, and the beſt Wine, called <hi>Vinum Tribianum.</hi> This Citie was greatly ampli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by <hi>Alphonſo</hi> the ſecond, Duke of <hi>Esté.</hi> 'Tis populous, and the inhabitants are noble and inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuous, and better natur'd than moſt of <hi>Italy;</hi> they being quick in their reſolutions, eaſie to be pacified when injur'd, debonnair and courteous in their en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment and treating of ſtrangers. Though they are ill and fooliſhly treated by ſome over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſorious <hi>Italians,</hi> whe injuriouſly nickname it <hi>Modena lapazza,</hi> Fooliſh <hi>Modena;</hi> it being a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licious and undeſerv'd reflection upon that people. The females are of a meek and patient temper, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther too amorous, nor too coy; too courtly, nor too peeviſh; as they are in other places, for the generality: They are very much applauded alſo by Mr. <hi>Warcup,</hi> in his Hiſtory of <hi>Venice,</hi> where he enumerates the ſeveral Cities of <hi>Italy</hi> in Verſe,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:57987:7"/>tranſlated out of the <hi>Italian;</hi> and concludes thus:</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>Foligno</hi>'s candi'd ſtreets most pleaſant are,</l>
               <l>The Ladies in <hi>Fano</hi> ſo ſmoothe and fair,</l>
               <l>That ſaid they are from heaven ſent to be:</l>
               <l>But <hi>Modena</hi> more happie is than ſhe.</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Modena</hi> hath been the Nurſery of many famous and learned men; ſome whereof are taken notice of by <hi>Nicolaus Leorinus Sileſius,</hi> a learned and ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant Poet, in his Catalogue of Learned men that flouriſhed in his Age.</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rbs Venetum Bembos loquitur Balboſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Poetas,</l>
               <l>Naugerioſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſuos;</l>
               <l>Mantua Virgilii, Capilupos numine plenos</l>
               <l>Caſtilioſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Duces;</l>
               <l>At Molſas Mutina &amp; Sadoletos jactat alumnos,</l>
               <l>Corteſioſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſuas, &amp;c.</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Modena</hi> has produced theſe eminent perſons:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hercules Rangonus. James Sadolet</hi> a man of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite Learning, <hi>Gregory Corteſius</hi> of the Order of <hi>Benedictines, Thomas Badias</hi> of the Fraternity of <hi>Praedicants,</hi> who were elected Cardinals by Pope <hi>Paul</hi> the third. She is alſo ennobled by <hi>Charles Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gonius</hi> a moſt learned man, and an eminent Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian. She is the Miſtreſs of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>go Rangonus</hi> Praeſul of <hi>Reggio,</hi> of <hi>Francis Maria Molza, John Franciſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus Furnius.</hi> It hath bred up ſome that were very
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:57987:7"/>much renown'd in War; as <hi>Nicolas</hi> and <hi>Gerard Rangonus, Hannibal</hi> and <hi>Guido</hi> both ſons of <hi>Nico<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las.</hi> There are many Noble Families in the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions of the Duke; as the <hi>Pii,</hi> the <hi>Mirandulani, Bonacelſii,</hi> &amp;c. of which we ſhall ſpeak more at large in the concluſion. But above all, the Family <hi>d'Esté</hi> who are now Lords of it; the Citie being very much ennobled and enriched by the conſtant reſidence of the Duke. Nor is ſhe without her Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tadel, wherein according to credible report there are ſtor'd up Arms for Forty thouſand men at leaſt: a very conſiderable buſineſs!</p>
            <p>The next thing that falls under our conſideration and deſcription, is the Citie of <hi>Reggio</hi> in this Duke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of <hi>Modena. Aemilia dein via pergenti, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xtra Seciae ripa omiſſa Regium Lepidi occurrit, ripae Crustuli laevae adpoſitum,</hi> ſaith <hi>Merula</hi> in his Coſmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graphy. As to its name, 'tis called by <hi>Tully</hi> in his Epiſtle to <hi>Caſſius</hi> and others <hi>Regium Lepidi:</hi> by <hi>Tacitus, Regium Lepidum:</hi> by <hi>Strabo,</hi> l. 5. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. by <hi>Ptolemy,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. by <hi>Antoninus, Regium</hi> onely, and at this day, 'tis commonly known by the name of <hi>Reggio.</hi> In this place here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore there was <hi>Forum Lepidi,</hi> as <hi>Festus</hi> obſerves. The inhabitants are called <hi>Regienſes,</hi> from <hi>Lepidus</hi> in <hi>Pliny;</hi> as alſo <hi>Regini, à Regio Julio.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nor hath Heaven been more propitious to this Citie, or Fortune more favourable than to <hi>Modena:</hi> for it hath run almoſt the ſame riſ<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> and taſted of the ſame miſery and misfortune. It was at firſt made a
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:57987:8"/>
               <hi>Romane</hi> Colony, as well as <hi>Modena; M. Aemilius Lepidus</hi> who gave it a name, <hi>T. Ebuſius Carus,</hi> and <hi>L. Quinctius Criſpinus,</hi> being then <hi>Triumviri.</hi> It was deſtroyed by the <hi>Goths,</hi> when they made incurſions into, and embaraſſed all <hi>Italy,</hi> under <hi>Alarico</hi> their King: the Citizens were conſtrained, by reaſon of the fury of an enraged and barbarous enemy, to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandon it, and flee to more ſecure retirements and places, till the <hi>Lombards</hi> were conquer'd and bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten out of <hi>Italy</hi> by <hi>Charles</hi> the Great, about the year 800; at what time by degrees the Citizens returned to their deſolate Citie, and began to reſtore, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pair, and immure it with a ſtrong Wall. It was go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verned by it ſelf for ſome time in liberty, after the manner of the other Cities in <hi>Italy;</hi> and this free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and liberty continued till the year 1286, and then it came under the Dominion of Earls and Princes; and 'twas firſt under the command of the Earls of <hi>Canoſſe,</hi> then thoſe of <hi>Esté,</hi> the <hi>Caeſars,</hi> the Kings of <hi>France;</hi> then it was ſubject to the Papal Sea, and had alſo the <hi>Foliani, Scaligers, Gonzagae,</hi> and <hi>Ottobuoni</hi> for its Lords. So <hi>Blondus, Antoninus, Platina,</hi> and <hi>Sabellicus.</hi> So far <hi>Morula. Heylin</hi> ſaith, When they were under the command of the Earls of <hi>Canoſſe,</hi> they grew weary of that Yoke, and recovered their Liberty; which being unable to maintain in thoſe buſtling times, they gave them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to <hi>Obizo</hi> the father of <hi>Azo, anno</hi> 1292. and after that, in the year 1326, to the Sea of <hi>Rome.</hi> Paſſing thorow many hands, it was at laſt ſold for 60000 Ducats to the <hi>Viſconti</hi> Lords of <hi>Milain, an.</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:57987:8"/>1370; and in the end recovered by the Houſe of <hi>Esté, anno</hi> 1409, and gave the Title of a Duke to <hi>Borſius</hi> Marqueſs of <hi>Ferrara,</hi> whom <hi>Frederick</hi> the 3. made Duke of <hi>Modena</hi> and <hi>Reggio, anno</hi> 1452. The Succeſſours of <hi>Borſius</hi> held the Eſtate toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, till the death of <hi>Alphonſo</hi> the firſt Duke, who dying without lawful iſſue, <hi>anno</hi> 1592, left his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate to <hi>Caeſar d'Esté</hi> his Nephew by a natural ſon, called <hi>Alphonſo</hi> alſo; between whom and Pope <hi>Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> the 8, a War was threatned for the whole; but at laſt comprimiſed upon theſe Conditions: <hi>That the Church of</hi> Rome <hi>ſhould have</hi> Ferrara, <hi>with all the Lands and Territories appertaining to it, as an Eſtate anciently held of that Sea: And that</hi> Modena <hi>and</hi> Reggio <hi>being Imperial Feifs, ſhould remain to</hi> Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar, <hi>but to be held in Fee of the Papal Throne: Duke</hi> Caeſar <hi>to have leave to carry away all his moveables, to ſell ſuch of his Lands as were not of the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Demain of the Dukedome; and to have one half of the Ordnance and Artillery.</hi> By which A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement, the Cities of <hi>Modena</hi> and <hi>Reggio</hi> became a new-erected State, diſtinct and independent of any other, each Citie being well Fortified, Gariſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and furniſhed with Ordnance for defence there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. But what they yield unto the Prince in the way of Revenue, and what Force he is able to raiſe out of his Eſtate, I cannot poſitively determine: but by the Tribute formerly paid unto the Popes for the Citie of <hi>Mutina,</hi> (now <hi>Modena</hi>) and the rich Territories of both Towns, and the great Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues of the Dukes of <hi>Ferrara;</hi> I conceive they
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:57987:9"/>cannot yeeld leſs than 100000 Crowns of yearly Income. Thus far <hi>Heylin</hi> in his <hi>Coſmography.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reggio</hi> (ſaith <hi>Merula</hi>) <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rbs eſt lauta, nobilis, fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quens; ſolo ſita valde fertili; loco pulchro, amoeno, plane<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> regio, unde illi quorundam judicio nomen.</hi> This Citie is built on the <hi>Via Aemilia,</hi> and named <hi>Regium Lepidi</hi> by <hi>Strabo, Cicero, Cornelius Tacitus,</hi> and other Authors. By whom it was built, is not certainly known; though 'tis reported by ſome to be erected by the <hi>Toſcans,</hi> who being expulſed, as <hi>Livy</hi> and <hi>Polybius</hi> affirm, the <hi>Gauls</hi> or <hi>French</hi> poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed it; and afterwards it was made a Colony by <hi>M. Aemilius Lepidus,</hi> one of the <hi>Triumviri; T. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butius Carus,</hi> and <hi>L. Quinctius Criſpinus,</hi> being the other two, as is before mentioned. Some contend that <hi>Marius Lepidus</hi> one of the ſaid <hi>Triumvirate,</hi> who divided the <hi>Romane</hi> Empire, was its Founder; others that it was built long before his time, but by him made a Colony.</p>
            <p>'Tis a noble, ſplendid, and well-peopled Citie, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounding with all things: it hath fair and ſpacious ſtreets, with ſumptuous ſtructures; as the magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent Church of S. <hi>Proſpero</hi> Biſhop of this Citie, where his corpſe is devoutly kept; having a very plentiful Revenue, and being adorn'd with excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Portraictures, but particularly with ſome Pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces drawn by the famous <hi>Correggio,</hi> worthy of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Fame. In the walls of the Orchard of the <hi>R. R. P. P. de Servi,</hi> was not long ſince diſcovered an Image of the holy Virgin, held in great eſteem there for its Miracles, with uncommon and ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:57987:9"/>(I had almoſt ſaid idolatrous) venera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reggio</hi> abounds with all neceſſaries for the uſe of man; the Soil is extraordinary fertil of all manner of Grain, and all ſorts of Fruits. White Wines it hath good ſtore, and a ſort of Wine call'd <hi>Vinum Hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volum,</hi> of its colour, being between a red and white. 'Tis very much fam'd and taken notice of, for the rare art of making Spurs, the beſt in <hi>Italy;</hi> and other Mechanical pieces in Ivory, politely and exactly done according to art.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Reggians</hi> are a people very courteous and affable, of a good mein and preſence, of preſent wit, and quick apprehenſion, vivacious and ſpright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and to be moulded and brought to any great or auguſt employment. The Women, as thoſe of <hi>Modena,</hi> are very milde, and the fineſt in all <hi>Italy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is adorn d with a Biſhoprick ſubject to the ſame Archbiſhop as <hi>Modena;</hi> and hath brought forth many famous men, who have rendred it very illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrious; as <hi>D. Maximus</hi> one of its Biſhops, <hi>Guido Sagaranus, Philip Caſolus, James Columbus, Charles Ruinus, Francis Belius, Julius Scarlatinus,</hi> famous Lawyers: <hi>Sebaſtianus Carradus,</hi> profoundly learned in the Greek and Latine Tongues; and <hi>Bartholo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mew Crottus,</hi> a great Poet of his time. It contains many noble Families; as the <hi>Signori Canoſſae, Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fredi, Fogliani,</hi> and <hi>Seſſi,</hi> who poſſeſs great Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips there, and have very noble and large Caſtles for their Apartments or Mannor-houſes.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:57987:10"/>
            <p>Now I have given you an account-of theſe two capital Cities of the great Dukedome of <hi>Modena:</hi> I will caſt my eye with a retroſpect upon ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther famous Caſtles, Towns and Places within their Territories, and acquaint you with ſome paſſages and rarities that may merit the obſervation, and gratifie the curioſity of the diligent and induſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Enquirer, that will make it his buſineſs to pry into them.</p>
            <p>On the left ſide of the River <hi>Po,</hi> ſaith my Author, there ſtands the <hi>Arx Stellata,</hi> a Caſtle fabriqued by <hi>Nicolas</hi> 3. of the Houſe of <hi>Esté,</hi> who was Marqueſs of <hi>Ferrara:</hi> but the greateſt part of it was in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs of time overthrown by the Legions of Pope <hi>Julius</hi> the 11, and the <hi>Venetians.</hi> And upon the Bank of the River <hi>Po</hi> is ſeen a new-built Town call'd <hi>Rovero,</hi> a neat and large place.</p>
            <p>Towards the South of <hi>Modena,</hi> under the <hi>Apen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nines,</hi> ſtand <hi>Formagine, Spezzano;</hi> and ten miles off, <hi>Saſſulo,</hi> a Noble and civil place, with a ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptuous Caſtle of the Family of the <hi>Pii,</hi> watred by the River <hi>Secchia,</hi> where is alſo a fair Church dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated to the bleſſed Virgin.</p>
            <p>About half a mile ſhort of <hi>Saſſulo,</hi> is the Temple of the Saint <hi>Maria Saſſutina,</hi> ſo called from the Caſtle <hi>Saſſulo</hi> ſituated at the very foot of the <hi>Apen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nine</hi> hills or mountains on the left ſide of the banks of <hi>Secchia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Upon theſe Mountains ſtand many other Villages and Hamlets, and are plainly viſible in the Eaſtern part of <hi>Modena.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:57987:10"/>
            <p>Theſe Caſtles were formerly ſubject to ſeveral Lords, and particularly to them of <hi>Monte,</hi> who were very powerful at that time in theſe Countries, and poſſeſſed all the Places in the <hi>Graffignana,</hi> which confines on <hi>Bologna;</hi> and among the reſt, <hi>Sestola</hi> and <hi>Fanano.</hi> Weſtward, the <hi>Alps</hi> of <hi>San Pellegrine</hi> appear to the view; and the Caſtle <hi>Acquario,</hi> fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous for its Baths, and their Medicinal waters; and from thence 'tis probably conjectur'd it takes its denomination. Then turning to the South, runs the <hi>Tyrrhene</hi> Sea, ſomewhat near <hi>Bologna.</hi> On the banks of the River <hi>Panaro</hi> ſtand <hi>Vetro</hi> and <hi>Spilim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berto,</hi> formerly call'd <hi>Spinum Lamberti,</hi> two Caſtles belonging to the <hi>Signori Rangoni.</hi> Four miles di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant from thence you finde <hi>Vignola,</hi> a Town dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified with a Marquiſate, ſubject to the <hi>Signori Buoncompagni,</hi> which borders upon the <hi>Bolognian</hi> Territories.</p>
            <p>Towards the North is ſituated the moſt Noble Caſtle, or rather Imperial Citie, call'd <hi>Carpi;</hi> which may deſervedly come in competition with many Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, if you conſider the populouſneſs or ingenuity of the People, and the ſuperfluity of all neceſſaries. It is honoured with the title of a Principality, and was for many years enjoyed by the <hi>Signori Pii;</hi> but at this day it is under the Duke of Modena.</p>
            <p>Then there is to be ſeen the ample, noble, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulent Monaſtery of S. <hi>Benedict Podolironus,</hi> built by <hi>Boniface</hi> the father of Counteſs <hi>Mathilde,</hi> and enlarged by the ſaid Counteſs, whoſe Sepulchre is there likewiſe. And <hi>Guardiſtallo,</hi> famous for two
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:57987:11"/>Councils held there, one under Pope <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rban</hi> the 8, and the other under <hi>Paſchal</hi> the 11: witneſs <hi>Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tina</hi> in the Hiſtory of their Lives, and <hi>Blondus</hi> in his fourteenth Book of <hi>Historical Relations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>On the Banks of the River <hi>Po,</hi> ſomewhat farther, <hi>Breſcello</hi> fronts you, call'd <hi>Brixillum</hi> by <hi>Pliny,</hi> in his third Book; and <hi>Plutarch,</hi> in the Life of <hi>Otho</hi> the Emperour: by <hi>Ptolemy,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and by <hi>Taci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus, Suetonius, Antoninus,</hi> and <hi>Paulus Diaconus.</hi> It was formerly a Citie, ſaith <hi>Leander,</hi> and taken by <hi>Anthare</hi> King of the <hi>Lombards,</hi> who diſmantled and levell'd the walls with the ground, according to <hi>Paulus Diaconus</hi> in his Continuation of <hi>Eutro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pius,</hi> l. 28. and <hi>Blondus</hi> in the 8 Book of his Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory.</p>
            <p>On the left hand of the banks of the River <hi>Len<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>za</hi> ſtands <hi>Tanedo,</hi> nam'd by <hi>Livy</hi> in many places, and <hi>Pliny</hi> (who affirms that there was a man there 120 years old) <hi>Tannetum;</hi> by <hi>Polybius, Tanetus;</hi> by <hi>Pto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemy,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and hence it is that <hi>Pliny</hi> calls the people <hi>Tanetani.</hi> It was ſubverted by <hi>Ceſe</hi> King of the <hi>Lombards,</hi> ſaith <hi>Paulus Diaconus;</hi> was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored, and reduced to the form that now it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears in, being at preſent a Village or Hamlet.</p>
            <p>In the Eaſtern part of <hi>Modena</hi> is a Chanel, upon which you may paſs by Boat 8 miles at length, till you arrive at <hi>Finale:</hi> then going on the River <hi>Panaro,</hi> where the Chanel diſembarques it ſelf into that River, is ſeen <hi>Buon Porto,</hi> and <hi>San Felice,</hi> much commended for generous Wines. Along the <hi>Aemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian</hi> way, three miles from <hi>Modena,</hi> runs the River
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:57987:11"/>
               <hi>Panaro,</hi> near which are the confines of the <hi>Modo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſi</hi> and <hi>Bologneſi,</hi> where <hi>Claudius</hi> the Conſul co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping with his enemies, took 15000 Priſoners, and 700 <hi>Ligurians.</hi> Nay farther, in this very place <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tari</hi> King of the <hi>Lombards</hi> routed the <hi>Romane</hi> Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, with the ſlaughter of 7000 Souldiers. Here alſo the Forces of the <hi>Modoneſi</hi> being diſcomfited by the <hi>Bologneſi, Euzo</hi> King of <hi>Sardegna,</hi> the ſon of <hi>Erderick</hi> the ſecond, was taken Priſoner. On the other ſide of <hi>Panaro</hi> is <hi>Novantola,</hi> with a Monaſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry famous both for its antiquity as well as ſtatelineſs, founded by <hi>Anſelmo,</hi> nearly related to <hi>Astolfo</hi> King of the <hi>Lombards,</hi> who was a redoubted Captain in their Army.</p>
            <p>Near the <hi>Aemilian</hi> way, between <hi>Bologna</hi> and <hi>Novantola,</hi> ſtands <hi>Santa Agata,</hi> a Caſtle erected by <hi>Barbaroſſa</hi> the Emperour; and <hi>Crevalcuore,</hi> former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly known by the name of <hi>Allegracuore,</hi> where the Army of <hi>Bernabo Viſconte</hi> Lord of <hi>Milain</hi> was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feated and put to the Rout.</p>
            <p>Next you go to <hi>San Giovanni,</hi> a Country very plentiful of Wheat and other Grain. On the left ſide of <hi>Via Aemilia</hi> ſtand <hi>Castiglione</hi> and <hi>Castel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>franco,</hi> 15 miles off of <hi>Bologna;</hi> where ſome few years paſt there was raiſed a moſt impregnable Fort by Pope <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rban</hi> the 8, and from him called <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rbano.</hi> Neer this Fort is the <hi>Foro di Galli,</hi> where <hi>Hirſius</hi> and <hi>Panſa,</hi> two <hi>Romane</hi> Conſuls, were engaged with <hi>M. Antonius;</hi> who obtained a glorious Victory, but withal their mortal wounds, whereof they both di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon the place, as is prementioned. Then there
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:57987:12"/>appear <hi>Purmanio, Bazanio,</hi> and <hi>Crepellano,</hi> three pleaſant Caſtles ſeated on thoſe hillocks that are at the foot of the <hi>Apennines.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>On the left hand of the <hi>Aemilian</hi> way, five miles from <hi>Bologna,</hi> are the Rivers <hi>Lavinio</hi> and <hi>Ghiron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> which meeting together with mutual embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, joyntly environ <hi>Forcelli</hi> in a triangular form, being diſtant from <hi>Via Aemilia</hi> one mile; where <hi>Octavianus, M. Antonius,</hi> and <hi>Marius Lepidus,</hi> ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the Monarchy between them. This <hi>Forcelli</hi> is now a <hi>Peninſula,</hi> though it may be perceived to have been an Iſlet formerly. Afterwards theſe two Rivers diſgorge themſelves into the <hi>Po.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Near <hi>Bologna</hi> there is ſeen a Stone-bridge of great length, which beſtrides the River from one ſide to the other; from whence 'tis but a ſmall and eaſie mile to <hi>Bologna.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now we come to the places contiguous and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jacent to <hi>Reggio;</hi> near which there appear certain Hills that erect their lofty creſt ſo pleaſantly, as does create delight in all Paſſengers; no leſs beautified and adorned with ſeveral fair Towns and Villages, than delicious Wines and Fruit-trees. Towards <hi>Parma</hi> you may take a view of a Caſtle (ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by its ſite) where <hi>Mathilde</hi> the Counteſs pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> the ſeventh from the ſnares and ambuſhes prepared for him by the Emperour <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth, an enemy to the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> but afterwards he (being a tender-conſcienc'd <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligioſo</hi>) repented of this imaginary and ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſititious
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:57987:12"/>Crime, and was led a Royal dance by his Confeſſor bare-foot and bare-headed in the midſt of Winter, through Ice and Snow, from this place to the ſaid Pope, to implore a Pardon for this his <hi>Pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cadillo,</hi> and obtained it with a courteous reception. A remarkable Inſtance, and notorious Precedent of the Tyranny, Haughtineſs, and Vain-glory of his Ironical, nick-nam'd Holineſs, who dares preſume ſo proudly and imperiouſly to inſult over, nay buf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foon a puiſſant Potentate, making him foot it bare in the depth of a hard Winter; to the Idolatrous Citie of his reſidence; and thereby run the riſ<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> of loſing his life, to gain a fruitleſs and inſignificant Pardon. But this he muſt do, or forfeit all his <hi>Rega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia,</hi> and be daily menaced with that ſilly Scar-crow, the Thunder of Excommunication. Thus Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy grows conſumptive, hangs the head, droops, and dwindles away to nothing, and ſo expires; <hi>King</hi> is a meer empty name, or the more glorious <hi>ſynonyma</hi> of Vaſſals, and <hi>Prince</hi> the more ſplendid name of Slave. Thus the Scepter warps to the Croſier, the Emperours Hat vails to the Biſhops Mitre, and the <hi>ſingle</hi> does obeyſance to the <hi>triple</hi> Crown. Thus Regal Authority, whoſe tender neck was ever un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>accuſtomed to the burden of a tame condeſcention, puts on the heavie Yoke of Pontifical rigorous im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition. Thus here you ſee the great moſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Ring crouch to Antichriſt, or being Crown-fallen as well as Creſt-fallen. Thus Majeſtie it ſelf inclines the reverend head, ſtoops low with a reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rential bow to kiſs that vulgarly-ador'd Pantofle,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:57987:13"/>which frequently proves but the gaudy covering of a Gowty toe.</p>
            <p>At this day, the moſt Noble Family of the <hi>Canoſſae</hi> are Lords of this Caſtle, and the reſt that encircle it; and a ſmall diſtance from this, ſtand the Caſtles and other places that belong to the <hi>Signori Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fredi.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Keeping the way on the Mountains, you come to <hi>Graffignana,</hi> where <hi>Castelnuovo</hi> is to be ſeen, which in times of yore was the Birth-place of many Illuſtrious perſons; and in this our modern age, of <hi>Giulio <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>r<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bano;</hi> Doctor and Apoſtolick Prothonotary, who liv'd in great repute and eſteem among Princes Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſhly inclin'd, and was highly applauded by the Fry of the Septuagint of Cardinals, that pay homage to, and revere the pretended and triple-Crown'd Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſor of the Fiſherman; who did a long time offici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate as Vicar-general, in lieu of the Miter'd Cardinal <hi>Linga Carnaro</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Padua;</hi> and in that qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity died, <hi>anno</hi> 1592. (May the ſame mortality and good fortune, in God's due time, attend the whole Conclave, that's my Litany.) His brother <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rban</hi> was Captain of the <hi>Venetian Militia,</hi> and <hi>Filippo <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rbano</hi> their Nephew.</p>
            <p>In your return to the <hi>Aemilian</hi> way, occurs the Caſtle of <hi>Scandiano,</hi> dignified with the Title of a Marquiſate, ſubject to the <hi>Signori Feni,</hi> noble and renown'd <hi>Vicentines.</hi> On the left hand lies the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle <hi>Roldo,</hi> belonging to the Houſe of the <hi>Seſſi,</hi> a Feudatory of the Emperour; with <hi>San Martino, Gonzaga</hi> the moſt ſplendid Village belonging to the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:57987:13"/>
               <hi>Gonzagae</hi> Princes of <hi>Mantua,</hi> and <hi>Muvilara.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Between <hi>Modena</hi> and <hi>Reggio, Correggio</hi> appears, not far from the River <hi>Lenza;</hi> a noble Caſtle, well govern'd, and as well peopled: it was called a citie of the Empire, and appertains to the moſt Illuſtrious Family of the <hi>Correggii:</hi> and where the River <hi>Lecchia</hi> dichotomizeth the <hi>Via Aemilia,</hi> ſtands a very ſtrong Caſtle call'd <hi>Ruberia,</hi> or <hi>Rubiera,</hi> by the Learned <hi>Herberia,</hi> erected as ſome conjecture by the <hi>Boiardi,</hi> and as others imagine by the <hi>Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brii</hi> of <hi>Parma;</hi> which had ſerveral Maſters till the year 1523, and then it fell into the hands of the Dukes of <hi>Ferrara,</hi> and was made famous by the birth of <hi>Antonius Codrus,</hi> a moſt polite <hi>Grecian,</hi> and expert Latiniſt, being a man of great Learning and vaſt Parts. This Caſtle is ſtrongly fortified with a well-made Bulwark or Rampart, and ſurrounded with many Hills, which adde much grace and beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to its ſituation, and renders the proſpect very delightful. From hence you paſs into a ſpacious and good Road, very commodious for all Travel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers that ſteer their courſe that way, and deſigne to arrive at the capital Citie <hi>Modena,</hi> of which we have already given you a large and exact deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption.</p>
            <p>In this Tract there are four <hi>Apennine</hi> hills, and as many Cities which are indebted to the Counteſs <hi>Mathilde</hi> for their foundation, <hi>viz. Bibianello, Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtelvitreo, Monte Zano,</hi> and <hi>Monte Luzco;</hi> all un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the command and juriſdiction of the Earls of <hi>Canoſſae.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:57987:14"/>
            <p>Having given you a court and true account of the Government, Riches, Force, Religion, Manners and Qualifications of the People of this ancient and illuſtrious Dukedom, as alſo the nature and quality of the Soyl and Climate; I ſhall by way of Corol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lary cloſe all with a ſhort relation of the Original, Antiquity, and Genealogie of the Dukes of the Houſe of <hi>Esté,</hi> and bring them down by deſcent to the moſt Illuſtrious perſon who at preſent is the undoubted and lawful Prince of the Dukedom of <hi>Modena.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Princes of the Houſe of <hi>Esté</hi> have been ſo conſiderable, and ſo much taken notice of both in Peace and War, that <hi>John Baptista Pigna</hi> hath with much induſtry and learning compoſed eight Books of the original, noble exploits and tranſactions of this Princely Family in <hi>Italy</hi> and other countries.</p>
            <p>As to their original he ſaith, that <hi>Ateste,</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander of the <hi>Heneti</hi> (now <hi>Venetians</hi>) after the ſacking and deſtruction of <hi>Troy,</hi> was driven into theſe parts with a conſiderable Navie, and built the Citie <hi>Atestia</hi> or <hi>Ateste,</hi> of his own name; and he called the whole Tract of ground <hi>Venetia:</hi> but the <hi>Latine</hi> degenerating by degrees from its puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, the Citie loſt the primitive e name of <hi>Atestia,</hi> and ſenſibly ſhrunk into that of <hi>Esté.</hi> This <hi>Ateſtes</hi> deſcended from the <hi>Atii,</hi> of the <hi>Poblilian</hi> Tribe in <hi>Rome,</hi> who becauſe they did eſpouſe the Quarrel of the <hi>Caeſars,</hi> did obtain ſo much grace and favour as to be Lords not onely of their own Country,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:57987:14"/>but alſo of all the Territories of <hi>Venice.</hi> And here the <hi>Atestini</hi> (for ſo they were call'd of old) began to b e in reputation: and theſe Princes do produce their Chronologie of 1200 years, to mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt and teſtifie their Grandeur in a continued Series down to this preſent Age.</p>
            <p>Thus the <hi>Atii</hi> became Maſters of a great part of <hi>Venice</hi> when <hi>Ateste</hi> was their capital Citie of Reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence: and the <hi>Romane</hi> Caeſars being then accuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to create a Magiſtracie conſiſting of eleven of the chief Citizens, and ſometimes a greater number, (who were alſo called <hi>Decuriones,</hi> becauſe at the firſt inſtitution ten onely were requir'd) <hi>Atius</hi> the ſon of <hi>C.</hi> of the laſt Race, and the firſt Author of the Family of the <hi>Atestini,</hi> did exerciſe this Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracie there. And this the Inſcription of an old Stone doth ſufficiently prove, which to this day is preſerv'd by theſe Princes. This <hi>C. Atius</hi> had two ſons; <hi>Aurelius,</hi> and <hi>Flavius.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ateste</hi> being thus built, and the Metropolis of <hi>Venetia,</hi> was called afterwards <hi>Esté,</hi> and had four Gates oppos'd to the four quarters of the heaven; the <hi>Black,</hi> the <hi>White,</hi> the <hi>Triumphal,</hi> and the <hi>Capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toline</hi> Gate, in the <hi>Romilian</hi> Tribe, ſaith the Author. It was founded by the <hi>Atii,</hi> ruin'd by <hi>Acarinus,</hi> and reſtor'd by <hi>Aldoardus;</hi> and then 'twas made an Earldome, afterwards created a Marquiſate, and enlarged; beſieged by the <hi>Paduans,</hi> taken by <hi>Eze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linus,</hi> recovered by <hi>Azo,</hi> burnt by <hi>Ezelinus,</hi> poſſeſs'd by thoſe of <hi>Padoa,</hi> and then reſtor'd to <hi>Azo,</hi> and afterwards to <hi>Albertus.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:57987:15"/>
            <p>Thus you have in ſhort a brief Narrative of the ancient <hi>Atii,</hi> the original of the <hi>Atestini,</hi> or <hi>Esten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> as our Modern Authors write them; which is the moſt known name; and they are uſually call'd the Dukes of <hi>Esté.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Family <hi>d'Esté,</hi> at preſent Dukes of <hi>Modena,</hi> which are accounted in the number of the 7 Great Princes of <hi>Italy,</hi> according to the ancient Diviſion, which are, the Pope, King of <hi>Spain,</hi> Duke of <hi>Savoy, Toſcany, Modena, Parma</hi> and <hi>Montoa;</hi> they derive their Pedegree from <hi>Allo</hi> Marqueſs of <hi>Esté</hi> who took upon him the Surname (which the Family is known by to this day) of the Citie <hi>Esté;</hi> and ſtill appertains to them <hi>de jure.</hi> He married <hi>Alda</hi> daughter to the Emperour <hi>Otho</hi> the firſt; which happened <hi>an.</hi> 1000. and he had with her for Dower <hi>Modena</hi> and <hi>Reggio. Theobaldo d'Esté, Otho</hi>'s Grandchilde, was ſeized of <hi>Ferrara</hi> in the year 1055, from Pope <hi>John</hi> the 12: but they were diſſeiz'd and abſolutely diſpoſſeſt of it by <hi>Clement</hi> the 8, <hi>anno</hi> 1598, after the deceaſe of <hi>Alfonſo</hi> the ſecond, for want of lawful Iſſue male: yet <hi>Caeſar d'Esté</hi> was then in being, who was ſon of <hi>Alfonſo</hi> by <hi>Laura Ferrareſs;</hi> and he of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered to clear it by manifeſt proof, that his father was lawfully married to his mother, and he the le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitimate Heir. But the Pope was too hard for him, being ſurely poſſeſt of that which he ſo greedily thirſted after. And that Family ſtill lays claim to it by a legal pretenſion. B ut the holy Father (and he you know is infallible) will prove him to be a natural ſon.</p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:57987:15"/>
            <p>Yet maugre all this oppoſition, the Duke is ſtill in poſſeſſion of the Dukedoms of <hi>Modena</hi> and <hi>Reg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gio,</hi> the Principalities of <hi>Carpi</hi> and <hi>Correggio,</hi> the Earldom of <hi>Roli,</hi> and the Lordſhips of <hi>Saſſevil, Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fagna,</hi> and <hi>Frignano,</hi> by the late Treaty of <hi>Piſa.</hi> Here was indeed a diſpute between him and the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal Crown about the Valleys of <hi>Comachio;</hi> but this was not ſo hot, b ut it cool'd at length, and was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cided upon theſe Conditions: The Prince being to receive 400000 Crowns for them; which were ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly paid, and 40000 more for damages, and ſome other advantageous terms. Theſe Lands which we have before ſpecified, together with thoſe which he poſſeſſeth in the Dukedome of <hi>Ferrara,</hi> yield him annually full 500000 Crowns. All his Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions are contiguous, and joining cloſe one to the other; which renders him more conſiderable; and his ſtrength and force conſiſts in the number of his people. <hi>Carfagnana</hi> alone (being a Province be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to him) is reported to have fourſcore and odde places well wall'd about, beſides ſeveral other Strong-holds. He is able upon urgent occaſions to lead into the Field 20000 of the Infantry, and 1000 of the Cavalry well arm'd and accoutred. And farther, he can without any inconveniencie whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever maintain and keep half of that number. His His Country, tis true, and cannot be denied, lies o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen to ſeveral bordering Princes; not for want of good places and well-fortified Caſtles, for he hath many ſeated at a very convenient diſtance; but the reaſon is, becauſe his <hi>Terroir</hi> or Land lies level, and upon even ground.</p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:57987:16"/>
            <p>The Princes of <hi>Modena</hi> follow the general Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ximes of their Neighbours, <hi>viz.</hi> to keep a good cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondence with <hi>Venice,</hi> which was always repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the Protectreſs of <hi>Italian</hi> Libertie: but ſince the loſs of <hi>Ferrara,</hi> they kept cloſe to the <hi>Spaniard,</hi> till their Intereſt of late wrought a change upon their inclinations. For Duke <hi>Francis</hi> was in the late <hi>Italian</hi> Wars made General of the French; and <hi>Mazarine</hi>'s Neece married to Prince <hi>Almerigo</hi> his ſon, who hath left a young ſon to ſucceed him. All things at preſent are managed by the advice of Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal <hi>d'Esté,</hi> Protector of the French Intereſt at <hi>Rome,</hi> and the ſole Promoter of the late Union of his Houſe to the French Crown. He is Uncle to the now Duke of <hi>Modena;</hi> a very active and ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring perſon, and hath made the world ſpeak honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably of him, for his actions both in Peace and War. He is extraordinarily well skill'd in the art of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealing his reſentments, and underſtands the old Motto: <hi>Qui neſcit diſſimulare,</hi> &amp;c. At <hi>Rome</hi> he keeps his Palace with more pomp and ſplendour than any of the Cardinalate: and though 'tis very much frequented by the Nobility, and a numerous train of people, yet they are all conſtantly and well paid. He is a Zealot in the French Cauſe; by whoſe friendſhip his Family is enriched and well moneyed, by reaſon of the late Generalſhip, as alſo the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try: for the Souldiers took up their Winter-quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters in <hi>Modena;</hi> which occaſioned a great reſort of the chief Officers, as well as inferiour perſons; and this did help the poor Populace to pay the Gabels,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:57987:16"/>with which they are heavily burthen'd. At preſent there is one of the Name and Relation, <hi>Carlo d'Esté;</hi> a Knight of the Order of the Fleece, who attended on the Empreſs.</p>
            <p>The Duke of <hi>Modena</hi> hath this advantage be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond moſt <hi>Italian</hi> Princes, that ſome of his Subjects have <hi>Feifs</hi> of the Empire. There are many great Families; as, the rich Earls <hi>di San Paolo,</hi> the <hi>Benti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vogli, Rangoni, Buoncompagni;</hi> the Marqueſſes <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>limberto, Peppoli, Gualengo, di Vignola,</hi> and <hi>Gualteri;</hi> the Earls <hi>Caprari, San Martino, di Molſa, di Mal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſia, Montecuculi, Taſſoni, Ferrareze, di Conoſcia,</hi> and ſome others. But all Princes and Republicks in <hi>Italy,</hi> the <hi>Venetian</hi> ſolely excepted, do homage, or pay Tribute to the Pope or Emperour; and the Duke of <hi>Modena</hi> among the reſt does Homage to the Emperour for his whole State. <hi>Ranuccio</hi> the Duke of <hi>Parma</hi> was married to the ſiſter of the late Duke, ſhe being his ſecond Wife, his former dying without Iſſue.</p>
            <p>The preſent Duke of <hi>Modena, Francis</hi> the ſecond, is very young; ſo that we have nothing to mention of his Perſon: and if he were of years, we muſt ſay of him, as of other Princes of <hi>Italy,</hi> They are extremely reſerv'd, live very retiredly, cautiouſly receiving Forreigners; ſo that ſtrangers rarely have admiſſion into their Courts, or free acceſs to their Perſons for any continuance. They live a kinde of recluſe and private life, affording no matter of obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation to the inquiſitive that viſit forraign Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries.</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:57987:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>JOSEPHA-MARIA <hi>d'Esté</hi> (at preſent the Il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtrious Dutcheſs of <hi>York</hi>) is Siſter to the above<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned <hi>Francis</hi> Duke of <hi>Modena,</hi> and daughter of <hi>Laura Martinozza</hi> the now Dutcheſs Dowager, by whom ſhe was accompanied to <hi>Dover,</hi> where her Nuptials were ſolemnly celebrated, being Married by the Reverend Dr. <hi>Crew,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Oxford,</hi> to the moſt Illuſtrious Prince, his Royal Highneſs JAMES Duke of <hi>York,</hi> whom God preſerve.</p>
            <p>To conclude all: The Arms of the Houſe of <hi>Esté,</hi> (the preſent Duke of <hi>Modena</hi> being of that Noble and Illuſtrious Family) is a Coat for its ſtrangeneſs much taken notice of, and is thus Bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zon'd.</p>
            <p>The Arms are <hi>Palewiſe,</hi> of three Pieces. Firſt, <hi>Partie per Feſs</hi> in the <hi>Chief, Or:</hi> an <hi>Eagle diſplayed, Sables; membred, langued, and crowned, Gules;</hi> and in <hi>baſe Azure, three Flowers de Lis</hi> within a <hi>Bordure indented, Or,</hi> and <hi>Gules.</hi> Secondly, <hi>Gules two Keys in Saltier,</hi> the one <hi>Or,</hi> the other <hi>Argent,</hi> charged in <hi>Feſs</hi> with an <hi>Eſcutcheon of pretence, Azure,</hi> ſuppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting an <hi>Eagle</hi> of the third <hi>membred,</hi> and <hi>crowned</hi> of the ſecond: over all, in <hi>Chief,</hi> a Papal Crown <hi>Or,</hi> garniſhed with ſundry Gems <hi>Azure</hi> and <hi>Purple.</hi> Thirdly: The third as the firſt, <hi>counterplaced.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now this Coat, upon the failer of the Houſe of <hi>Ferrara,</hi> belongs to the Family <hi>d'Esté,</hi> ſince Dukes of <hi>Modena</hi> and <hi>Reggio.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:57987:17"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
